<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY MAY "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MAY</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY MUST-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>MUST NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY OPTIONAL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>OPTIONAL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY RECOMMENDED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY REQUIRED "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>REQUIRED</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHALL-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHALL NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY SHOULD-NOT "<bcp14 xmlns='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext" xmlns:ed="http://greenbytes.de/2002/rfcedit" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" number="7617"  category="std" xml:lang="en" obsoletes="2617" x:maturity-level="proposed">

  <!--<x:feedback template="mailto:http-auth@ietf.org?subject={docname},%20%22{section}%22&amp;body=&lt;{ref}&gt;:"/>-->

	<front>
  <title abbrev="'Basic' HTTP Authentication Scheme">The 'Basic' HTTP Authentication Scheme</title>
  <author initials="J. F." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian F. Reschke">
    <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Hafenweg 16</street>
        <city>Muenster</city><region>NW</region><code>48155</code>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </postal>
      <email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email>	
      <uri>http://greenbytes.de/tech/webdav/</uri>	
    </address>
  </author>

  <date year="2015" month="September"/>
  
  <area>Security</area>
  <workgroup>HTTPAuth</workgroup>
  <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
  <keyword>authentication scheme</keyword>
  <keyword>basic authentication scheme</keyword>
  
  <abstract>
    <t>
      This document defines the "Basic" Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)
      authentication scheme, which transmits credentials as user-id/password
      pairs, encoded using Base64.
    </t>
  </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
<section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
<t>
  This document defines the "Basic" Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)
  authentication scheme, which transmits credentials as user-id/password pairs,
  encoded using Base64 (HTTP authentication schemes are
  defined in <xref target="RFC7235"/>).
</t>
<t>
  This scheme is not considered to be a secure method of user authentication
  unless used in conjunction with some external secure system such as TLS
  (Transport Layer Security, <xref target="RFC5246"/>), as the user-id and
  password are passed over the network as cleartext.
</t>
<t>
  The "Basic" scheme previously was defined in <xref target="RFC2617" x:fmt="of" x:sec="2"/>.
  This document updates the definition, and also addresses internationalization issues
  by introducing the 'charset' authentication parameter (<xref target="charset"/>).
</t>
<t>
  Other documents updating RFC 2617 are "Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Authentication"
  (<xref target="RFC7235"/>, defining the authentication framework),
  "HTTP Digest Access Authentication" (<xref target="RFC7616"/>,
  updating the definition of the "Digest" authentication scheme), and
  "HTTP Authentication-Info and Proxy-Authentication-Info Response Header Fields"
  (<xref target="RFC7615"/>). Taken together, these four documents obsolete RFC 2617.
</t>

<section title="Terminology and Notation"  anchor="terminology.and.notation">
<t>
  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
  "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
  are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
<t>
   The terms "<x:dfn>protection space</x:dfn>" and "<x:dfn>realm</x:dfn>" are
   defined in <xref target="RFC7235" x:fmt="of" x:sec="2.2" />. 
</t>
<t>
  The terms "<x:dfn>(character) repertoire</x:dfn>" and 
  "<x:dfn>character encoding scheme</x:dfn>" are defined in
  <xref target="RFC6365" x:fmt="of" x:sec="2"/>.
</t>
</section>  
</section>  

<section title="The 'Basic' Authentication Scheme" anchor="basic.authentication.scheme">
<t>
   The Basic authentication scheme is based on the model that the
   client needs to authenticate itself with a user-id and a password for
   each protection space ("realm"). The realm value is a free-form string
   that can only be compared for equality with other realms on that
   server. The server will service the request only if it can validate
   the user-id and password for the protection space applying to the 
   requested resource.
</t>
<t>
   The Basic authentication scheme utilizes the Authentication Framework as
   follows.
</t>
<t>
   In challenges:
   <list style="symbols">
      <t>The scheme name is "Basic".</t>
      <t>The authentication parameter 'realm' is &REQUIRED; (<xref target="RFC7235" x:fmt="," x:sec="2.2"/>).</t>
      <t>The authentication parameter 'charset' is &OPTIONAL; (see <xref target="charset"/>).</t>
      <t>No other authentication parameters are defined &mdash; unknown parameters &MUST;
      be ignored by recipients, and new parameters can only be defined by revising this
      specification.</t>
   </list>
</t>
<t>
  See also <xref target="RFC7235" x:sec="4.1"/>, which
  discusses the complexity of parsing challenges properly.
</t>
<t>
  Note that both scheme and parameter names are matched case-insensitively.
</t>
<t>
  For credentials, the "token68" syntax defined in <xref target="RFC7235" x:fmt="of" x:sec="2.1"/>
  is used. The value is computed based on user-id and password as defined below.
</t>
<t>
   Upon receipt of a request for a URI within the protection space that lacks
   credentials, the server can reply with a challenge using the
   401 (Unauthorized) status code (<xref target="RFC7235"
   x:fmt="," x:sec="3.1"/>) and the WWW-Authenticate header field
   (<xref target="RFC7235" x:fmt="," x:sec="4.1"/>).
</t>
<figure>
  <preamble>For instance:</preamble>
<artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="   ">
HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
Date: Mon, 04 Feb 2014 16:50:53 GMT
WWW-Authenticate: Basic realm="WallyWorld"

</artwork>
<postamble>where "WallyWorld" is the string assigned by the server to identify
   the protection space.</postamble>
</figure>
<t>
   A proxy can respond with a similar challenge using the 407 (Proxy Authentication Required)
   status code (<xref target="RFC7235"
   x:fmt="," x:sec="3.2"/>) and the Proxy-Authenticate header field (<xref target="RFC7235"
   x:fmt="," x:sec="4.3"/>).
</t>
<t>
   To receive authorization, the client
   <list style="numbers">
      <t>obtains the user-id and password from the user,</t>
      <t>constructs the user-pass by concatenating the user-id, a single colon (":") character, and the password,</t>
      <t>encodes the user-pass into an octet sequence (see below for a discussion of character encoding schemes),</t>
      <t>and obtains the basic-credentials by encoding this octet sequence using Base64 (<xref target="RFC4648" x:fmt="," x:sec="4"/>) into a sequence of US-ASCII characters (<xref target="RFC0020"/>).</t>
   </list>
</t>
<t>
  The original definition of this authentication scheme failed to
  specify the character encoding scheme used to convert the user-pass into
  an octet sequence. In practice, most implementations chose either a locale-specific
  encoding such as ISO-8859-1 (<xref target="ISO-8859-1"/>), or UTF-8
  (<xref target="RFC3629"/>). For backwards compatibility reasons, this specification
  continues to leave the default encoding undefined, as long as it is compatible
  with US-ASCII (mapping any US-ASCII character to a single octet matching the
  US-ASCII character code).
</t>
<t>
  The user-id and password &MUST-NOT; contain any control characters (see
  "CTL" in <xref target="RFC5234" x:fmt="of" x:sec="B.1"/>).
</t>
<t>
  Furthermore, a user-id containing a colon character is invalid, as
  the first colon in a user-pass string separates user-id and password
  from one another; text after the first colon is part of the password.
  User-ids containing colons cannot be encoded in user-pass strings.
</t>
<t>  
  Note that many user agents produce user-pass strings without checking
  that user-ids supplied by users do not contain colons; recipients
  will then treat part of the username input as part of the password.
</t>
<figure>
<preamble>
   If the user agent wishes to send the user-id "Aladdin" and password
   "open sesame", it would use the following header field:</preamble>
<artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
Authorization: Basic QWxhZGRpbjpvcGVuIHNlc2FtZQ==
</artwork></figure>

<section title="The 'charset' auth-param" anchor="charset">
<t>
  In challenges, servers can use the 'charset' authentication parameter
  to indicate the character encoding scheme they expect the user
  agent to use when generating "user-pass" (a sequence of octets). This
  information is purely advisory.
</t>
<t>
  The only allowed value is "UTF-8"; it is to be matched case-insensitively 
  (see <xref target="RFC2978" x:fmt="," x:sec="2.3"/>). It indicates that
  the server expects character data to be converted to Unicode
  Normalization Form C ("NFC"; see <xref target="RFC5198" x:fmt="of" x:sec="3"/>)
  and to be encoded into octets using the UTF-8 character encoding scheme
  (<xref target="RFC3629"/>).
</t>
<t>
  For the user-id, recipients &MUST; support all characters defined
  in the "UsernameCasePreserved" profile defined in
  <xref target="RFC7613" x:fmt="of" x:sec="3.3"/>, with the exception of the 
  colon (":") character.
</t>
<t>
  For the password, recipients &MUST; support all characters defined
  in the "OpaqueString" profile defined in
  <xref target="RFC7613" x:fmt="of" x:sec="4.2"/>.
</t>
<t>  
  Other values are reserved for future use.
</t>
<x:note>
  <t>
   <x:h>Note:</x:h> The 'charset' is only defined on challenges, as Basic authentication
   uses a single token for credentials ('token68' syntax); thus, the
   credentials syntax isn't extensible.
  </t>
</x:note>
<x:note>
  <t>
   <x:h>Note:</x:h> The name 'charset' has been chosen for consistency with
   <xref target="RFC2831" x:fmt="of" x:sec="2.1.1"/>. A better name would have
   been 'accept-charset', as it is not about the message it appears in, but
   the server's expectation.
  </t>
</x:note>
<figure>
  <preamble>In the example below, the server prompts for authentication in the "foo" realm,
  using Basic authentication, with a preference for the UTF-8 character encoding scheme:</preamble>
  <artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
WWW-Authenticate: Basic realm="foo", charset="UTF-8"
</artwork>
  <postamble>Note that the parameter value can be either a token or a quoted
  string; in this case, the server chose to use the quoted-string notation.</postamble>
</figure>
<t>
  The user's name is "test", and the password is the string "123" followed by
  the Unicode character U+00A3 (POUND SIGN). Using the character encoding
  scheme UTF-8, the user-pass becomes:
</t>
<figure><artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
't' 'e' 's' 't' ':' '1' '2' '3' pound
74  65  73  74  3A  31  32  33  C2  A3  
</artwork></figure>
<t>
  Encoding this octet sequence in Base64 (<xref target="RFC4648" x:fmt="," x:sec="4"/>) yields:
</t>
<figure><artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
dGVzdDoxMjPCow==
</artwork></figure>
<t>
  Thus, the Authorization header field would be:
</t>
<figure><artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
Authorization: Basic dGVzdDoxMjPCow==
</artwork></figure>
<t>
  Or, for proxy authentication:
</t>
<figure><artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
Proxy-Authorization: Basic dGVzdDoxMjPCow==
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="Reusing Credentials" anchor="reusing.credentials">
<t>
   Given the absolute URI (<xref target="RFC3986" x:fmt="," x:sec="4.3"/>)
   of an authenticated request, the <x:dfn>authentication scope</x:dfn> of
   that request is obtained by removing all characters after the last 
   slash ("/") character of the path component ("hier_part"; see <xref target="RFC3986" x:fmt="," x:sec="3"/>).
   A client &SHOULD; assume that resources identified
   by URIs with a prefix-match of the authentication scope are also
   within the protection space specified by the realm value of
   that authenticated request.
</t>   
<t>
   A client &MAY; preemptively send the corresponding Authorization header
   field with requests for resources in
   that space without receipt of another challenge from the server.
   Similarly, when a client sends a request to a proxy, it &MAY; reuse a
   user-id and password in the Proxy-Authorization header field without
   receiving another challenge from the proxy server.
</t>
<figure>
  <preamble>
    For example, given an authenticated request to:
  </preamble>
  <artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
http://example.com/docs/index.html
</artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <preamble>
    requests to the URIs below could use the known credentials:
  </preamble>
  <artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
http://example.com/docs/
http://example.com/docs/test.doc
http://example.com/docs/?page=1
</artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <preamble>
    while the URIs
  </preamble>
  <artwork type="example" x:indent-with="   ">
http://example.com/other/
https://example.com/docs/
</artwork>
<postamble>
would be considered to be outside the authentication scope.
</postamble>
</figure>
<t>
  Note that a URI can be part of multiple authentication scopes (such
  as "http://example.com/" and "http://example.com/docs/"). This specification
  does not define which of these should be treated with higher priority.
</t>
</section>

</section>  

<section title="Internationalization Considerations" anchor="internationalization.considerations">
<t>
  User-ids or passwords containing characters outside the US-ASCII
  character repertoire will cause interoperability issues, unless both
  communication partners agree on what character encoding scheme is to be
  used. Servers can use the new 'charset' parameter (<xref target="charset"/>)
  to indicate a preference of "UTF-8", increasing the probability that clients
  will switch to that encoding.
</t>
<t>
  The 'realm' parameter carries data that can be considered textual; however,
  <xref target="RFC7235"/> does not define a way to reliably transport non-US-ASCII
  characters. This is a known issue that would need to be addressed in a
  revision to that specification. 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security.considerations">
<t>
   The Basic authentication scheme is not a secure method of user
   authentication, nor does it in any way protect the entity, which is
   transmitted in cleartext across the physical network used as the
   carrier. HTTP does not prevent the addition of enhancements (such as
   schemes to use one-time passwords) to Basic authentication.
</t>
<t>
   The most serious flaw of Basic authentication is that it results in
   the cleartext transmission of the user's password over
   the physical network. Many other authentication schemes address this
   problem.
</t>
<t>
   Because Basic authentication involves the cleartext transmission of
   passwords, it &SHOULD-NOT; be used (without enhancements such as HTTPS <xref target="RFC2818"/>) to protect
   sensitive or valuable information.
</t>
<t>
   A common use of Basic authentication is for identification purposes
   &mdash; requiring the user to provide a user-id and password as a means
   of identification, for example, for purposes of gathering accurate
   usage statistics on a server. When used in this way it is tempting to
   think that there is no danger in its use if illicit access to the
   protected documents is not a major concern. This is only correct if
   the server issues both user-id and password to the users and, in
   particular, does not allow the user to choose his or her own password.
   The danger arises because naive users frequently reuse a single
   password to avoid the task of maintaining multiple passwords.
</t>
<t>
   If a server permits users to select their own passwords, then the
   threat is not only unauthorized access to documents on the server but
   also unauthorized access to any other resources on other systems that
   the user protects with the same password. Furthermore, in the
   server's password database, many of the passwords may also be users'
   passwords for other sites. The owner or administrator of such a
   system could therefore expose all users of the system to the risk of
   unauthorized access to all those other sites if this information is not
   maintained in a secure fashion. This raises both security and privacy
   concerns (<xref target="RFC6973"/>). If the same user-id and password
   combination is in use to access other accounts, such as an email or health
   portal account, personal information could be exposed.
</t>
<t>
   Basic authentication is also vulnerable to spoofing by counterfeit
   servers. If a user can be led to believe that she is connecting to a
   host containing information protected by Basic authentication when,
   in fact, she is connecting to a hostile server or gateway, then the
   attacker can request a password, store it for later use, and feign an
   error. Server implementers ought to guard against this sort of
   counterfeiting; in particular, software components that can take over control
   over the message framing on an existing connection need to be used carefully
   or not at all (for instance: NPH ("Non-Parsed Header") scripts as
   described in <xref target="RFC3875" x:fmt="of" x:sec="5"/>).
</t>
<t>
   Servers and proxies implementing Basic authentication need to store user
   passwords in some form in order to authenticate a request. These passwords
   ought to be stored in such a way that a leak of the password data
   doesn't make them trivially recoverable. This is especially important
   when users are allowed to set their own passwords, since users are known
   to choose weak passwords and to reuse them across authentication realms. 
   While a full discussion of good password hashing techniques is
   beyond the scope of this document, server operators ought to make an
   effort to minimize risks to their users in the event of a password
   data leak.  For example, servers ought to avoid storing user passwords in
   plaintext or as unsalted digests.  For more discussion about modern
   password hashing techniques, see the "Password Hashing Competition"
   (<eref target="https://password-hashing.net"/>). 
</t>
<t>
   The use of the UTF-8 character encoding scheme and of normalization introduces additional
   security considerations; see <xref target="RFC3629" x:fmt="of" x:sec="10"/>
   and <xref target="RFC5198" x:fmt="of" x:sec="6"/>
   for more information.
</t>

</section>  

<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana.considerations">
<t>
  IANA maintains the "Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) Authentication Scheme Registry" (<xref target="RFC7235"/>)
  at <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/http-authschemes"/>.
</t>
<t>
  The entry for the "Basic" authentication scheme has been updated to
  reference this specification.
</t>
</section>  

  </middle>
  <back>
  
<references title="Normative References">
  
  <reference anchor='RFC0020'>
    <front>
      <title>ASCII format for network interchange</title>
      <author initials='V.' surname='Cerf' fullname='Vint Cerf'/>
      <date year='1969' month='October' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='STD' value='80' />
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='20' />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC2119">
    <front>
      <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
      <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner"/>
      <date month="March" year="1997"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC2978">
    <front>
      <title>IANA Charset Registration Procedures</title>
      <author initials="N." surname="Freed" fullname="N. Freed"/>
      <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="J. Postel"/>
      <date year="2000" month="October"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="19"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2978"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC3629">
    <front>
      <title>UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646</title>
      <author initials="F." surname="Yergeau" fullname="F. Yergeau">
        <organization>Alis Technologies</organization>
        <address><email>fyergeau@alis.com</email></address>
      </author>
      <date month="November" year="2003"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="STD" value="63"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3629"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC3986">
    <front>
      <title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
      <author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'/>
      <author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'/>
      <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'/>
      <date month='January' year='2005'></date>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC4648">
    <front>
      <title>The Base16, Base32, and Base64 Data Encodings</title>
      <author fullname="S. Josefsson" initials="S." surname="Josefsson"/>
      <date year="2006" month="October"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo value="4648" name="RFC"/>
  </reference>  

  <reference anchor="RFC5198">  
    <front>
      <title>Unicode Format for Network Interchange</title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin"/>
      <author initials="M." surname="Padlipsky" fullname="M. Padlipsky"/>
      <date year="2008" month="March"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5198"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC5234">
    <front>
      <title abbrev="ABNF for Syntax Specifications">Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
      <author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="Dave Crocker" role="editor">
        <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
        <address>
          <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
        </address>  
      </author>
      <author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="Paul Overell">
        <organization>THUS plc.</organization>
        <address>
          <email>paul.overell@thus.net</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <date month="January" year="2008"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC6365">
    <front>
      <title>Terminology Used in Internationalization in the IETF</title>
      <author initials="P." surname="Hoffman" fullname="P. Hoffman"/>
      <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin"/>
      <date year="2011" month="September"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="166"/>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6365"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC7235">
    <front>
      <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Authentication</title>
      <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Fielding"/>
      <author fullname="Julian F. Reschke" initials="J. F." role="editor" surname="Reschke"/>
      <date month="June" year="2014"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7235"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC7613">
    <front>
      <title>Preparation, Enforcement, and Comparison of Internationalized Strings Representing Usernames and Passwords</title>
      <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre"/>
      <author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikow"/>
      <date year="2015" month="August"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7613"/>
  </reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">  

  <reference anchor="RFC7615">
    <front>
      <title>HTTP Authentication-Info and Proxy-Authentication-Info Response Header Fields</title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian Reschke"/>
      <date month="September" year="2015"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7615"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC7616">
    <front>
      <title>HTTP Digest Access Authentication</title>
      <author initials="R." surname="Shekh-Yusef" fullname="Rifaat Shekh-Yusef" role="editor"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="Ahrens" fullname="David Ahrens"/>
      <author initials="S." surname="Bremer" fullname="Sophie Bremer"/>
      <date month="September" year="2015"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7616"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="ISO-8859-1">
    <front>
      <title>Information technology -- 8-bit single-byte coded graphic character sets -- Part 1: Latin alphabet No. 1</title>
      <author>
        <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="1998"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="8859-1:1998"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC2617">
    <front>
      <title abbrev="HTTP Authentication">HTTP Authentication: Basic and Digest Access Authentication</title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Franks" fullname="John Franks"/>
      <author initials="P.M." surname="Hallam-Baker" fullname="Phillip M. Hallam-Baker"/>
      <author initials="J.L." surname="Hostetler" fullname="Jeffery L. Hostetler"/>
      <author initials="S.D." surname="Lawrence" fullname="Scott D. Lawrence"/>
      <author initials="P.J." surname="Leach" fullname="Paul J. Leach"/>
      <author initials="A." surname="Luotonen" fullname="Ari Luotonen"/>
      <author initials="L." surname="Stewart" fullname="Lawrence C. Stewart"/>
      <date month="June" year="1999"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2617"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor='RFC2818'>
    <front>
      <title>HTTP Over TLS</title>
      <author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='Eric Rescorla'>
        <organization>RTFM, Inc.</organization>
        <address><email>ekr@rtfm.com</email></address>
      </author>
      <date year='2000' month='May' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2818' />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC2831">
    <front>
      <title>Using Digest Authentication as a SASL Mechanism</title>
      <author initials="P." surname="Leach" fullname="P. Leach"/>
      <author initials="C." surname="Newman" fullname="C. Newman"/>
      <date year="2000" month="May"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2831"/>
  </reference>

  <reference  anchor='RFC3875' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3875'>
    <front>
      <title>The Common Gateway Interface (CGI) Version 1.1</title>
      <author initials='D.' surname='Robinson' fullname='D. Robinson'/>
      <author initials='K.' surname='Coar' fullname='K. Coar'/>
      <date year='2004' month='October' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3875'/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC5246">
     <front>
        <title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2</title>
        <author initials="T." surname="Dierks" fullname="T. Dierks"/>
        <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="E. Rescorla"/>
        <date year="2008" month="August" />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5246" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor='RFC6973'>
    <front>
      <title>Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>
      <author initials='A.' surname='Cooper' fullname='Alissa Cooper'/>
      <author initials='H.' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='Hannes Tschofenig'/>
      <author initials='B.' surname='Aboba' fullname='Bernard Aboba'/>
      <author initials='J.' surname='Peterson' fullname='Jon Peterson'/>
      <author initials='J.' surname='Morris' fullname='John B. Morris'/>
      <author initials='M.' surname='Hansen' fullname='Marit Hansen'/>
      <author initials='R.' surname='Smith' fullname='Rhys Smith'/>
      <date year='2013' month='July' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6973' />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC7231">
    <front>
      <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>
      <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Fielding">
        <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
        <address><email>fielding@gbiv.com</email></address>
      </author>
      <author fullname="Julian F. Reschke" initials="J. F." role="editor" surname="Reschke">
        <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
        <address><email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email></address>
      </author>
      <date month="June" year="2014" />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7231"/>
  </reference>

</references>

<section title="Changes from RFC 2617">
<t>
  The scheme definition has been rewritten to be consistent with newer
  specifications such as <xref target="RFC7235"/>.
</t>
<t>
  The new authentication parameter 'charset' has been added. It is purely
  advisory, so existing implementations do not need to change, unless
  they want to take advantage of the additional information that
  previously wasn't available.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Deployment Considerations for the 'charset' Parameter">
<section title="User Agents">
<t>
  User agents not implementing 'charset' will continue to work as
  before, ignoring the new parameter.
</t>
<t>
  User agents that already default to the UTF-8 encoding implement
  'charset' by definition.
</t>
<t>
  Other user agents can keep their default behavior and switch to UTF-8
  when seeing the new parameter.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Servers">
<t>
  Servers that do not support non-US-ASCII characters in credentials do
  not require any changes to support 'charset'.
</t>
<t>
  Servers that need to support non-US-ASCII characters, but cannot use
  the UTF-8 character encoding scheme will not be affected; they will continue
  to function as well or as badly as before.
</t>
<t>
  Finally, servers that need to support non-US-ASCII characters and can
  use the UTF-8 character encoding scheme can opt in by specifying the 'charset'
  parameter in the authentication challenge. Clients that do understand the
  'charset' parameter will then start to use UTF-8, while other clients will
  continue to send credentials in their default encoding, broken credentials,
  or no credentials at all. Until all clients are upgraded to support UTF-8,
  servers are likely to see both UTF-8 and "legacy" encodings in requests.
  When processing as UTF-8 fails (due to a failure to decode as UTF-8 or a
  mismatch of user-id/password), a server might try a fallback to the previously
  supported legacy encoding in order to accommodate these legacy clients.
  Note that implicit retries need to be done carefully; for instance, some
  subsystems might detect repeated login failures and treat them as
  a potential credentials-guessing attack.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Why not simply switch the default encoding to UTF-8?">
<t>
  There are sites in use today that default to a local character encoding scheme, such as
  ISO-8859-1 (<xref target="ISO-8859-1"/>), and expect user agents to use that encoding. Authentication on these sites
  will stop working if the user agent switches to a different encoding, such as UTF-8.
</t>
<t>
  Note that sites might even inspect the User-Agent header field
  (<xref target="RFC7231" x:fmt="," x:sec="5.5.3"/>) to decide which character encoding scheme to expect from the client.
  Therefore, they might support UTF-8 for some user agents, but default to
  something else for others. User agents in the latter group will have to
  continue to do what they do today until the majority of these servers
  have been upgraded to always use UTF-8.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
<t>
  This specification takes over the definition of the "Basic" HTTP Authentication
  Scheme, previously defined in RFC 2617. We thank John Franks,
  Phillip M. Hallam-Baker, Jeffery L. Hostetler, Scott D. Lawrence,
  Paul J. Leach, Ari Luotonen, and Lawrence C. Stewart for their work on
  that specification, from which significant amounts of text were borrowed.
  See <xref target="RFC2617" x:fmt="of" x:sec="6"/> for further acknowledgements.
</t>
<t>
  The internationalization problem with respect to the character encoding scheme
  used for user-pass was reported as a Mozilla bug back in the year 2000 (see <eref target="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=41489"/>
  and also the more recent <eref target="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=656213"/>).
  It was Andrew Clover's idea to address it using a new auth-param.
</t>
<t>
  We also thank the members of the HTTPAUTH Working Group and other reviewers, namely, Stephen Farrell, Roy Fielding,
  Daniel Kahn Gillmor, Tony Hansen, Bjoern Hoehrmann, Kari Hurtta, Amos Jeffries, Benjamin Kaduk, Michael Koeller, Eric Lawrence, Barry Leiba, James Manger,
  Alexey Melnikov, Kathleen Moriarty, Juergen Schoenwaelder, Yaron Sheffer, Meral Shirazipour, Michael Sweet, and Martin Thomson for feedback on this revision.
</t>
</section>  

  </back>
</rfc>