<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "lib/rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc2616 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.2616.xml'> 
  <!ENTITY rfc4918 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.4918.xml'> 
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> 
  <!ENTITY rfc3864 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.3864.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5226 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5023 PUBLIC '' 'lib/ref/reference.RFC.5023.xml'>
  
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc strict="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext html-pretty-print="prettyprint https://cdn.rawgit.com/google/code-prettify/master/loader/run_prettify.js"?>

<rfc submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="yes" ipr="trust200902"
     number="7240" xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
  <front> 
    <title abbrev="HTTP Prefer"> 
      Prefer Header for HTTP
    </title> 
 
    <author initials="J.M." surname="Snell" fullname="James M Snell"> 
      <address> 
        <email>jasnell@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author> 
    
    <date month="June" year="2014" /> 
 
    <area>Applications</area> 

    <keyword>http</keyword> 
    <keyword>prefer</keyword> 
 
    <abstract> 
      <t>This specification defines an HTTP header field that can be
      used by a client to request that certain behaviors be employed
      by a server while processing a request.</t> 
    </abstract> 
 
  </front> 
  
  <middle> 
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction"> 
 
      <t>Within the course of processing an HTTP request, there are typically
      a range of required and optional behaviors that a server or intermediary 
      can employ. These often manifest in a variety of subtle and not-so-subtle 
      ways within the response.</t>
      
      <t>For example, when using the HTTP PUT method to modify a resource -- 
      similar to that defined for the Atom Publishing Protocol <xref target="RFC5023" /> --
      the server is given the option of returning either a complete representation 
      of a modified resource or a minimal response that indicates only the successful
      completion of the operation. The selection of which type of response to 
      return to the client generally has no bearing on the successful processing
      of the request but could, for instance, have an impact on what actions the 
      client must take after receiving the response. That is, returning a 
      representation of the modified resource within the response can allow the 
      client to avoid sending an additional subsequent GET request.</t>
      
      <t>Similarly, servers that process requests are often faced with decisions
      about how to process requests that may be technically invalid or incorrect 
      but are still understandable. It might be the case that the server is able to 
      overlook the technical errors in the request but still successfully process
      the request. Depending on the specific requirements of the application and 
      the nature of the request being made, the client might or might not 
      consider such lenient processing of its request to be appropriate.</t>
      
      <t>While the decision of exactly which behaviors to apply in these cases lies 
      with the server processing the request, the server might wish to defer to the 
      client to specify which optional behavior is preferred.</t>
      
      <t>Currently, HTTP offers no explicitly defined means of expressing
      the client's preferences regarding the optional aspects of handling of a 
      given request. While HTTP does provide the Expect header -- which can be used 
      to identify mandatory expectations for the processing of a request -- use of 
      the field to communicate optional preferences is problematic:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The semantics of the Expect header field are such that intermediaries and 
          servers are required to reject any request that states unrecognized or 
          unsupported expectations.</t>
          <t>While the Expect header field is end to end, the HTTP specification
          requires that the header be processed hop by hop. That is, every interceding
          intermediary that handles a request between the client and the origin
          server is required to process an expectation and determine whether it is
          capable of appropriately handling it.</t>
        </list>
      </t>


      <t>The must-understand semantics of the Expect header make it a poor choice for the expression of optional preferences.</t>
      
      <t>Another option available to clients is to utilize Request URI query-string
      parameters to express preferences. However, any mechanism that alters the URI 
      can have undesirable effects, such as when caches record the altered URI.</t>

      <t>As an alternative, this specification defines a new HTTP request header 
      field that can be used by clients to request that optional behaviors be applied
      by a server during the processing the request. Additionally, a handful of 
      initial preference tokens for use with the new header are defined.</t> 
      
      <t>In this document, the key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", 
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" 
      are to be  interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t> 
 
      <section title="Syntax Notation">
        <t>This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) 
        notation of <xref target="RFC5234"/> and includes, by reference,
        the "token", "word", "OWS", and "BWS" rules and the #rule 
        extension as defined within Sections 3.2.1 and 3.2.4 of 
        <xref target="RFC7230"/>; as well as 
        the "delta-seconds" rule defined in Section 8.1.3 of 
        <xref target="RFC7231"/>.</t>
      </section>
 
    </section> 
        
    <section title="The Prefer Request Header Field" anchor="prefer"> 
    
      <t>The Prefer request header field is used to indicate that particular 
      server behaviors are preferred by the client but are not required for 
      successful completion of the request.  Prefer is similar in nature to the 
      Expect header field defined by Section 6.1.2 of <xref target="RFC7231"/> 
      with the exception that servers are allowed to ignore stated preferences.</t> 
      
      <figure><preamble>ABNF:</preamble><artwork type="abnf2616"> 
  Prefer     = "Prefer" ":" 1#preference
  preference = token [ BWS "=" BWS word ] 
               *( OWS ";" [ OWS parameter ] )
  parameter  = token [ BWS "=" BWS word ]
      </artwork></figure> 
  
      <t>This header field is defined with an extensible syntax to allow for future
      values included in the <xref target="registry">Registry of Preferences</xref>. 
      A server that does not recognize or is unable to comply with
      particular preference tokens in the Prefer header field of a request
      MUST ignore those tokens and continue processing instead of signaling
      an error.</t> 
      

      <t> Empty or zero-length values
on both the preference token and within parameters are equivalent to
no value being specified at all.  The following, then, are 
      equivalent examples of a "foo" preference with a single "bar" parameter.</t>
      
      <figure><artwork type="example">
  Prefer: foo; bar
  Prefer: foo; bar=""
  Prefer: foo=""; bar
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>An optional set of parameters can be specified for any preference token. 
      The meaning and application of such parameters is dependent on the definition 
      of each preference token and the server's implementation thereof. There is
      no significance given to the ordering of parameters on any given preference.</t>
      
      <t>For both preference token names and parameter names, comparison is 
      case insensitive while values are case sensitive regardless of whether 
      token or quoted-string values are used.</t> 
       
      <t>The Prefer header field is end to end and MUST be forwarded 
      by a proxy if the request is forwarded unless Prefer is explicitly
      identified as being hop by hop using the Connection header field 
      defined by <xref target="RFC7230"/>, Section 6.1.</t> 
      
      <t>In various situations, a proxy might determine that it is capable of 
      honoring a preference independently of the server to which the request 
      has been directed. For instance, an intervening proxy might be capable 
      of providing asynchronous handling of a request using 202 (Accepted) 
      responses independently of the origin server. Such proxies can choose to 
      honor the "respond-async" preference on their own regardless of whether or not the 
      origin is capable or willing to do so.</t> 
      
      <t>Individual preference tokens MAY define their own requirements and 
      restrictions as to whether and how intermediaries can apply the preference to 
      a request independently of the origin server.</t> 
      
      <t>A client MAY use multiple instances of the Prefer header field in a
      single message, or it MAY use a single Prefer header field with
      multiple comma-separated preference tokens. If multiple Prefer header
      fields are used, it is equivalent to a single Prefer header field
      with the comma-separated concatenation of all of the tokens. For
      example, the following are equivalent:</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>Multiple Prefer header fields defining three distinct
        preference tokens:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /foo HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Prefer: respond-async, wait=100
Prefer: handling=lenient
Date: Tue, 20 Dec 2011 12:34:56 GMT
</artwork></figure>
  
      <figure><preamble>A single Prefer header field defining the same three
        preference tokens:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /foo HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Prefer: handling=lenient, wait=100, respond-async
Date: Tue, 20 Dec 2011 12:34:56 GMT
</artwork></figure>

      <t>To avoid any possible ambiguity, individual preference tokens 
      SHOULD NOT appear multiple times within a single request. If any preference 
      is specified more than once, only the first instance is to be considered. 
      All subsequent occurrences SHOULD be ignored without signaling an error or 
      otherwise altering the processing of the request. This is the only case
      in which the ordering of preferences within a request is considered to 
      be significant.</t>
      
      <t>Due to the inherent complexities involved with properly 
      implementing server-driven content negotiation, effective caching,
      and the application of optional preferences, implementers 
      are urged to exercise caution when using preferences in a way that 
      impacts the caching of a response and SHOULD NOT use the Prefer
      header mechanism for content negotiation. If a server supports 
      the optional application of a preference that might result in a 
      variance to a cache's handling of a response entity, a Vary header 
      field MUST be included in the response listing the Prefer header 
      field regardless of whether the client actually used Prefer in the 
      request. Alternatively, the server MAY include a Vary header with 
      the special value "*" as defined by <xref target="RFC7231"/>, Section 8.2.1.
      Note, however, that use of the "Vary: *" header will make it impossible
      for a proxy to cache the response.</t>
      
      <t>Note that while Preference tokens are similar in structure to 
      HTTP Expect tokens, the Prefer and Expect header fields serve very 
      distinct purposes and preferences cannot be used as expectations.</t>
  
      <section title="Examples">
      
      <t>The following examples illustrate the use of various preferences 
      defined by this specification, as well as undefined extensions for 
      strictly illustrative purposes:</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>1. Return a 202 (Accepted) response for asynchronous 
      processing if the request cannot be processed within 10 seconds. An 
      undefined "priority" preference is also specified:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: respond-async, wait=10
Prefer: priority=5

{...}
</artwork></figure>

      <figure><preamble>2. Use lenient processing:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: Lenient

{...}
</artwork></figure>
       
      <figure><preamble>3. Use of an optional, undefined parameter on the 
      return=minimal preference:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: return=minimal; foo="some parameter"

{...}
</artwork></figure>
       
      </section>
 
    </section> 

    <section title="The Preference-Applied Response Header Field" anchor="preference-applied">
      
      <t>The Preference-Applied response header MAY be included within a
      response message as an indication as to which Prefer tokens were
      honored by the server and applied to the processing of a request.</t>

      <figure><preamble>ABNF:</preamble><artwork type="abnf2616"> 
  Preference-Applied = "Preference-Applied" ":" 1#applied-pref
  applied-pref = token [ BWS "=" BWS word ]
      </artwork></figure>

      <t>The syntax of the Preference-Applied header differs from that of 
      the Prefer header in that parameters are not included.</t>

      <t>Use of the Preference-Applied header is only necessary when it is 
      not readily and obviously apparent that a server applied a given preference 
      and such ambiguity might have an impact on the client's handling of the 
      response. For instance, when using either the "return=representation" or 
      "return=minimal" preferences, a client application might not be capable of 
      reliably determining if the preference was (or was not) applied simply by 
      examining the payload of the response. In such a case, the Preference-Applied 
      header field can be used.</t>

      <figure><preamble>Request:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
PATCH /my-document HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: application/example-patch
Prefer: return=representation

[{"op": "add", "path": "/a", "value": 1}]
</artwork></figure>

      <figure><preamble>Response:</preamble><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json
Preference-Applied: return=representation
Content-Location: /my-document

{"a": 1}
</artwork></figure>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Preference Definitions" anchor="definitions">  
     
      <t>The following subsections define an initial set of preferences.
      Additional preferences can be registered for convenience and/or to
      promote reuse by other applications.  This specification establishes
      an IANA registry of preferences (see <xref target="registry"/>).</t>
                
    <section title="The &quot;respond-async&quot; Preference" anchor="respond-async">
      <t>The "respond-async" preference indicates that the client prefers
      the server to respond asynchronously to a response. For instance, in the case
      when the length of time it takes to generate a response will exceed 
      some arbitrary threshold established by the server, the server can 
      honor the "respond-async" preference by returning a 202 (Accepted) response.</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>ABNF:</preamble><artwork type="abnf2616">
  respond-async = "respond-async"
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>The key motivation for the "respond-async" preference is to facilitate 
      the operation of asynchronous request handling by allowing the 
      client to indicate to a server its capability and preference for 
      handling asynchronous responses.</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example request specifying the "respond-async" preference:</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /collection HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: respond-async

{Data}
</artwork></figure>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example asynchronous response using 202 (Accepted):</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
HTTP/1.1 202 Accepted
Location: http://example.org/collection/123
</artwork></figure>
            
      <t>While the 202 (Accepted) response status is defined by 
      <xref target="RFC7231"/>, little guidance is given on 
      how and when to use the response code and the process for determining
      the subsequent final result of the operation is left entirely undefined. Therefore,
      whether and how any given server supports asynchronous responses is an 
      implementation-specific detail that is considered to be out of the scope
      of this specification.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="The &quot;return=representation&quot; and &quot;return=minimal&quot; Preferences" anchor="return"> 
      <t>The "return=representation" preference indicates that the client prefers
      that the server include an entity representing the current state of the 
      resource in the response to a successful request.</t>
      
      <t>The "return=minimal" preference, on the other hand, indicates that the client wishes
      the server to return only a minimal response to a successful request.
      Typically, such responses would utilize the 204 (No Content) status, but other
      codes MAY be used as appropriate, such as a 200 (OK)  status with a zero-length
      response entity. The determination of what constitutes an appropriate minimal response
      is solely at the discretion of the server.</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>ABNF:</preamble><artwork type="abnf2616">
  return = "return" BWS "=" BWS ("representation" / "minimal")
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>When honoring the "return=representation" preference, the returned 
      representation might not be a representation of the effective request URI
      when the request is affecting another resource. In such cases, the 
      Content-Location header can be used to identify the URI of the returned
      representation.</t>
      
      <t>The "return=representation" preference is intended to provide
      a means of optimizing communication between the client and server
      by eliminating the need for a subsequent GET request to retrieve the 
      current representation of the resource following a modification.</t>
      
      <t>After successfully processing a modification request such
      as a POST or PUT, a server can choose to return either an entity describing
      the status of the operation or a representation of the modified resource
      itself. While the selection of which type of entity to return, if any at all,
      is solely at the discretion of the server, the "return=representation" preference --
      along with the "return=minimal" preference defined below -- allow the 
      server to take the client's preferences into consideration while 
      constructing the response.</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example request specifying the "return=representation" preference:</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
PATCH /item/123 HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: application/example-patch
Prefer: return=representation

1c1
&lt; ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ
---
&gt; BCDFGHJKLMNPQRSTVWXYZ
</artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example response containing the resource representation:</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Location: http://example.org/item/123
Content-Type: text/plain
ETag: "d3b07384d113edec49eaa6238ad5ff00"

BCDFGHJKLMNPQRSTVWXYZ
</artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <t>In contrast, the "return=minimal" preference can reduce the amount 
      of data the server is required to return to the client following a request. 
      This can be particularly useful, for instance, when communicating with 
      limited-bandwidth mobile devices or when the client simply 
      does not require any further information about the result of a 
      request beyond knowing if it was successfully processed.</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example request specifying the "return=minimal" preference:</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /collection HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: return=minimal

{Data}
</artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example minimal response:</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
HTTP/1.1 201 Created
Location: http://example.org/collection/123
</artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <t>The "return=minimal" and "return=representation" preferences are 
      mutually exclusive directives. It is anticipated that there will never 
      be a situation where it will make sense for a single request to include 
      both preferences. Any such requests will likely be the result of a 
      coding error within the client. As such, a request containing both 
      preferences can be treated as though neither were specified.</t>
      
    </section> 
              
    <section title="The &quot;wait&quot; Preference" anchor="wait">
      <t>The "wait" preference can be used to establish an upper bound on the 
      length of time, in seconds, the client expects it will take the server 
      to process the request once it has been received. In the case that 
      generating a response will take longer than the time specified, 
      the server, or proxy, can choose to utilize an asynchronous processing 
      model by returning -- for example -- a 202 (Accepted) response.</t>

      <figure><preamble>ABNF:</preamble><artwork type="abnf2616">
  wait = "wait" BWS "=" BWS delta-seconds
      </artwork></figure>

      <t>It is important to consider that HTTP messages spend some time 
      traversing the network and being processed by intermediaries.  This 
      increases the length of time that a client will wait for a response 
      in addition to the time the server takes to process the request.  
      A client that has strict timing requirements can estimate these factors 
      and adjust the wait value accordingly.</t>

      <t>As with other preferences, the "wait" preference could be ignored.
      Clients can abandon requests that take longer than they are
      prepared to wait.</t>
            
      <figure><preamble>For example, a server receiving the following 
      request might choose to respond asynchronously if processing the 
      request will take longer than 10 seconds:</preamble>
      <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /collection HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: respond-async, wait=10

{Data}
</artwork></figure>
      
    </section>
     
    <section title="The &quot;handling=strict&quot; and &quot;handling=lenient&quot; Processing Preferences" anchor="handling">
    
    <t>The "handling=strict" and "handling=lenient" preferences indicate, 
    at the server's discretion, how the client wishes the server to 
    handle potential error conditions that can arise in the processing of a
    request. For instance, if the payload of a request contains various 
    minor syntactical or semantic errors, but the server is still capable of 
    comprehending and successfully processing the request, a decision must be
    made to either reject the request with an appropriate "4xx" error response
    or go ahead with processing. The "handling=strict" preference can be used to indicate 
    that, while any particular error may be recoverable, the client would prefer 
    that the server reject the request. The "handling=lenient" preference, on the other
    hand, indicates that the client wishes the server to attempt to process the 
    request.</t>
    
    <figure><preamble>ABNF:</preamble><artwork type="abnf2616">
  handling = "handling" BWS "=" BWS ("strict" / "lenient")
    </artwork></figure>
    
    <figure><preamble>An example request specifying the "strict" preference:</preamble>
    <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
POST /collection HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Content-Type: text/plain
Prefer: handling=strict
</artwork>
    </figure>
    
    <t>The "handling=strict" and "handling=lenient" preferences are 
    mutually exclusive directives. It is anticipated that there will never 
    be a situation where it will make sense for a single request to include 
    both preferences. Any such requests will likely be the result of a coding 
    error within the client. As such, a request containing both preferences 
    can be treated as though neither were specified.</t>
    
    </section>
           
    </section>
      
    <section title="IANA Considerations"> 
 
      <t>The 'Prefer' and 'Preference-Applied' header fields have been added
      to the "Permanent Message Header Field Names" registry defined in <xref target="RFC3864"/>
      (http://www.iana.org/assignments/message-headers).</t>
        
    <t><list> 
    <t>Header field name: Prefer</t>  
    <t>Applicable Protocol: HTTP</t>
    <t>Status: Standard</t>
    <t><![CDATA[Author: James M Snell <jasnell@gmail.com>]]></t>
    <t>Change controller: IETF</t>
    <t>Specification document: this specification, <xref target="prefer"/></t>
    </list></t> 
    
    <t><list> 
    <t>Header field name: Preference-Applied</t>  
    <t>Applicable Protocol: HTTP</t>
    <t>Status: Standard</t>
    <t><![CDATA[Author: James M Snell <jasnell@gmail.com>]]></t>
    <t>Change controller: IETF</t>
    <t>Specification document: this specification, <xref target="preference-applied"/></t>
    </list></t> 
      
      <section title="The Registry of Preferences" anchor="registry"> 
      
        <t>IANA has created a new registry, "HTTP Preferences",
        under the "Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) Parameters" registry.
        New registrations will use the Specification Required policy 
        <xref target="RFC5226"/>. The requirements for registered 
        preferences are described in <xref target="definitions" />.</t>

        <t>Registration requests consist of the completed registration template
        below, typically published in the required specification.  However, to
        allow for the allocation of values prior to publication, the Designated
        Expert can approve registration based on a separately submitted
        template once they are satisfied that a specification will be published.
        Preferences can be registered by third parties if the Designated Expert 
        determines that an unregistered preference is widely deployed and not 
        likely to be registered in a timely manner.</t>

        <t>The registration template is:</t>

        <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>Preference: (A value for the Prefer request header field that
	    conforms to the syntax rule given in <xref target="prefer"/>)</t> 
            <t>Value: (An enumeration or description of possible values for the preference token).</t>
            <t>Optional Parameters: (An enumeration of optional parameters, and their values, associated with the preference token).</t>
            <t>Description:</t> 
            <t>Reference:</t>
            <t>Notes: [optional]</t>
          </list> 
        </t> 
        
        <t>The "Value" and "Optional Parameters" fields MAY be omitted from the 
        registration template if the specific preference token definition does not 
        define either.</t>

        <t>Registration requests should be sent to the &lt;ietf-http-wg@w3.org&gt;
        mailing list, marked clearly in the subject line (e.g., "NEW PREFERENCE
        - example" to register an "example" preference). Within at most 14 days 
        of the request, the Designated Expert(s) will either approve or deny 
        the registration request, communicating this decision to the review list 
        and IANA.  Denials should include an explanation and, if applicable, 
        suggestions as to how to make the request successful.</t>
        
        <t>The Expert Reviewer shall ensure:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>That the requested preference name conforms to the token rule 
            in <xref target="prefer"/> and that it is not identical to any other 
            registered preference name;</t> 
            <t>That any associated value, parameter names, and values conform
            to the relevant ABNF grammar specifications in <xref target="prefer"/>;</t>
            <t>That the name is appropriate to the specificity of the 
            preference; i.e., if the semantics are highly specific to a particular
            application, the name should reflect that, so that more general
            names remain available for less specific uses.</t>
            <t>That requested preferences do not constrain servers, clients, or any 
            intermediaries to any behavior required for successful 
            processing; and </t>
            <t>That the specification document defining the preference includes 
            a proper and complete discussion of any security considerations
            relevant to the use of the preference.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
      </section> 
      
      <section title="Initial Registry Contents">
      
      <t>The "HTTP Preferences" registry's initial contents are:</t>
      
      <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 

            <t>Preference: respond-async</t> 
            <t>Description: Indicates that the client prefers that
               the server respond asynchronously to a request.</t> 
            <t>Reference: [this specification], <xref target="respond-async" /></t>
          </list> 
        </t> 
      
      <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>Preference: return</t> 
            <t>Value: One of either "minimal" or "representation"</t>
            <t>Description: When the value is "minimal", it indicates that the 
              client prefers that the server return a minimal response to a
	      request. When the value is "representation", it indicates that the
	      client prefers that the server include a representation of the
	      current state of the resource in response to a request.</t> 
            <t>Reference: [this specification], <xref target="return" /></t>
          </list> 
        </t> 
      
      <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>Preference: wait</t> 
            <t>Description: Indicates an upper bound to the length of 
            time the client expects it will take for the server to process 
            the request once it has been received.</t> 
            <t>Reference: [this specification], <xref target="wait"/></t>
          </list> 
        </t> 

      <t> 
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>Preference: handling</t> 
            <t>Value: One of either "strict" or "lenient"</t>
            <t>Description: When value is "strict", it indicates that the client 
              wishes the server to apply strict validation and error handling 
              to the processing of a request. When the value is "lenient", it
	      indicates that the client wishes the server to apply lenient
	      validation and error handling to the processing of the
	    request.</t>  
            <t>Reference: [this specification], <xref target="handling"/></t>
          </list> 
        </t> 
 
      </section>
      
    </section> 
    <section title="Security Considerations"> 
      <t>Specific preferences requested by a client can introduce security 
      considerations and concerns beyond those discussed within
      <xref target="RFC7230">HTTP/1.1</xref> and its
      associated specification documents (see <xref target="RFC7230" /> for the list of associated works). Implementers need to 
      refer to the specifications and descriptions of each preference to 
      determine the security considerations relevant to each.</t> 
      
      <t>A server could incur greater costs in attempting to comply with a
      particular preference (for instance, the cost of providing a
      representation in a response that would not ordinarily contain one; or
      the commitment of resources necessary to track state for an
      asynchronous response).  Unconditional compliance from a server could
      allow the use of preferences for denial of service.  A server can
      ignore an expressed preference to avoid expending resources that it
      does not wish to commit.</t>
               
    </section> 
  </middle> 
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> 
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3864;
      &rfc5226;


      &rfc5234;

<!--      &part1; companion document -->
<reference anchor='RFC7230'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy Fielding' role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Reschke' fullname='Julian Reschke' role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2014' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7230' />

</reference>


<!--      &part2; companion document -->

<reference anchor='RFC7231'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy Fielding' role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Reschke' fullname='Julian Reschke' role='editor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' year='2014' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7231' />

</reference>

    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5023;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc> 
 
